Guide to the American Studies Department records, 1953-1998 RG0082
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
American Studies Department records
1953-1998
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
George Washington University. American Studies Dept.
RG0082
13.75 Linear Feet
Collection includes memos, syllabi, course descriptions, student papers, reports, by-laws, correspondence, meeting minutes, comprehensive exams, and newsletters.
Box UP0001
Box UP0002
Restrictions on Access
Series 3 is closed to research for 25 years from date of record creation.
Series 1, 4, and 7 contain restricted material. Access to student records is governed by the federal Family Educational Rights and Privacy Act (FERPA), which protects the privacy of student education records. Student records are closed for 100 years from date of record creation.
Acquisition Information
Materials acquired through transfers from American Studies Department.
Historical or Biographical Note
Robert W. Bolwell founded what is now known as the American Studies Department in 1938. He had an A.B. degree from Case Western University, M.A. and Ph.D. degrees from Columbia University, and was a member of Phi Beta Kappa. He was a professor of English and American Literature and taught at GW from 1920-57. In 1938 he established the American Thought and Civilization major, and for twenty-five years it resided as a special program with in the English Department. In 1968 American Studies left the English Department, to establish itself as a separate program with departmental status. In line with changing social as well as academic interests, the program's first director, Robert Walker, took the lead in recruiting the College's first black professor, J. Saunders Redding, who The New York Times once called "probably the most eminent Negro writer of nonfiction in the country." The program added affiliations with the Library of Congress and Smithsonian Institution.
In the 1970's professors Bernard Mergen, Howard Gillette, Letitia Woods Brown, and Frederick Gutheim brought with them interests in African-American studies, urban and social history, as well as popular and material culture and added courses which helped grow the program. In 1980, courses in folklore were expanded under the direction of John Vlach. The arrival of Marcus Cunliffe as University professor and the expansion of the program's journal "American Studies International" added further stature, and in the coming years both the undergraduate and graduate programs were strengthened.
The Department currently offers three degrees: B.A., M.A., and Ph.D. The faculty and students who make up the American Studies Department combine interests drawn from a variety of perspectives and methods of inquiry: history, folklife, cultural studies, literary analysis, as well as the study of art, architecture, and visual culture. However, most faculty and students find their intellectual pursuits intersecting at some point around questions of public culture and/or public history. Students at all levels develop individualized, interdisciplinary programs of study in consultation with faculty advisors.
Since 1975, George Washington University has offered a unique interdisciplinary Master's program in historic preservation through its departments of American Studies and History. The program affords a strong intellectual perspective on critical issues in the preservation and a sound practical training for the field.
The Department published the journal "American Studies International."
N.B. This history note was written in 2005
Collection Scope and Content
Materials in this collection include memos, syllabi, course descriptions, student papers, reports, by-laws, correspondence, meeting minutes, comprehensive exams, and newsletters. They range in date from 1953 to 1998, and were transferred to the University Archives by the Chair of the Department of American Studies. Note: Not all series are processed. Ask staff for assistance.
Collection Organization
Organized into eight series: American Studies program, six series of general files, artifacts.
Foggy Bottom (Washington, D.C.); Washington (D.C.); Bolwell, Robert Whitney; George Washington University
- American Studies program, 1953-1998; RG0082 Series 1; 0.25 Linear feet (Box 1)
  Conditions Governing Access
  Access to student records is governed by the federal Family Educational Rights and Privacy Act (FERPA), which protects the privacy of student education records. Student records in this series are closed for 100 years from date of record creation.
  Scope and Contents note
  This series includes syllabi, student papers, brochures, correspondence, and reports from the American Studies program. They range in date from 1953 to 1998.
  - American Studies program, 1953-1988 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - American Studies program - brochures, 1965-1985 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - American Studies program - diary of Robert Bolwell, founder of program, 1933 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - American Studies program - syllabi and student papers, 1972-1998 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Telecommunications Department, 1960-1990 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Telecommunications Studies, Center for, 1960-1984 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- General records, RG0082 Series 2; 1 Linear foot
  This series contains historic preservation m.a. course development, GW campus plan and preservation, and course outlines.
  - PEARCE Report on Historic Preservation at GW, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - National Trust: Survey of Preservation Education, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - National Trust: Paul Sprague and Richard Haipt, undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Committee for Program, undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - American Civilization 277: Spring Semester Outlines, undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Historic Preservation and American Studies, undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - GW Campus Plan and Preservation, undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Historic Preservation: GW MA course development, undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Miscellaneous materials, undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Department files, 1966-1985; RG0082 Series 3; 3 Linear feet
  This series contains memos, schedules, syllabi, course descriptions, and historic preservation program. These records cover the dates 1966-85.
  - Orientation, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Summer Sessions, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Orientation, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Orientation Fall, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Job Vacancies, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Departmental Memos, 1981-1982 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Summer, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Dept'l Memos, 1980-1981 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Summer Schedule, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Dept'l Memos, 1979-1980 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Linton, Calvin, 1977-1980 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Orientation, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Summer School, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Dept'l Memos, 1978-1979 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Orientation -- Grad., Undergrad - Fall, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Summer School, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Orientation -- Grad., Undergrad - Spring, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Correspondence, 1977-1978 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Orientation -- Grad., Undergrad - Fall, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Dept'l Memos, 1977-1978 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Senior Seminar, 1977-1978 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Dept'l Memos, 1976-1977 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Summer School, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Dept'l Memos, 1975-1976 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Linton, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Summer School, 1974-1975 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Dept'l Memos, 1974-1975 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Dept'l Memos, 1973-1974 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - High School Program, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Dept'l Memos, 1970-1974 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Dept'l Memos, 1970-1971 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Col. Coll. - Linton, 1970-1976 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Dept'l Business, 1968-1970 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Brochure Announcement, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Faculty Grant Proposals: Horton, Gillette, 1982-1983 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Smithsonian Fellowship - NEH Proposals, 1976-1977 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - NEH Summer Institute, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - National Museum Act Grant, 1977-1978 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - National Museum Act - Appleton, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - National Museum Act, 1976-1977 (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - National Museum Act, 1975-1976 (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - NEH Proposal GW/LC, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - NEH Proposal - Fellowships, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - NEH Grants - Museum Related (Smithsonian Inst.), undated (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - Graduate Program, 1983 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Graduate PhD Survey, 1979 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Graduate Review, 1978 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - PhD Comprehensives, 1966-1968 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Student Handouts, Past, undated (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Undergrad AmStd Ad hoc Review Committee, 1985 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Undergrad Review, 1977 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Undergrad Majors, 1974 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Memos: Undergrad Program, undated (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - UG COMPS (OLD), undated (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - AmCiv, 1970-1979 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Am Civ, 1971 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Anthro 163 Visual Comunication, undated (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - 179-80 Senior Seminar, undated (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - AmCv 184 Contemporary America, undated (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - AmCiv/Hist 186 Urban History, undated (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - AmCiv 188 Urban Issues, undated (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - AmCiv 192, undated (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - AmCiv 255-256 American Seminar, undated (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - AmCiv 280 Urban History, undated (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - AmCiv 289, undated (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - AmCiv/U&RP 290 International Preservation, undated (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - 290.20 Hist Res Bermuda, undated (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - AmCiv 701 Sport, Leisure & Play, undated (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - AmCiv 701 Am Conservatism, undated (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Folklore Grant Proposal -- NEH, undated (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - LC Program: origins-66 Lib of Congress, undated (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Course Annotations, undated (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Syllabi -- Fall, 1983 (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Course Description - Spring, 1983 (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Course Syllabi - Fall, 1982 (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Course Listings - Spring, 1982 (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - Syllabi - Fall, 1981 (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - Syllabi - Spring, 1981 (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - Fall - Syllabi, 1980 (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - Syllabi - Summer, 1980 (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - Syllabi - Fall, 1979 (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - Spring Listings, 1979 (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - Syllabi - Fall, 1978 (Box 2, Folder 39)
  - Courses - Summer, 1978 (Box 2, Folder 40)
  - Syllabi - Spring, 1978 (Box 2, Folder 41)
  - Courses - Spring, 1977 (Box 2, Folder 42)
  - Course Syllabi - Fall, 1977 (Box 2, Folder 43)
  - Course Syllabi, 1975-1976 (Box 2, Folder 44)
  - Course Syllabi, 1975 (Box 2, Folder 45)
  - Letitia Brown, undated (Box 2, Folder 46)
  - Am Std Program/History, undated (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Brochures-Part Copies/GWU, undated (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Redding, J. Saunders, undated (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Lenthall Houses, undated (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Folklore Newsletter, undated (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - AmCiv/ExpHum 721: Neighborhood Theory &Practice - Spring, 1978 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Folklore, 1980 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Folklore - Summer, 1980 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Historic Preservation, 1982-1983 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Historic Preservation Report, 1981 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - HP Students Past & Present, undated (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Data on HP Students Past & Present, undated (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - HP Careers, 1975 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - HP Careers, 1976 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - GW-LC Program, 1978-1979 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Historic Preservation, 1978-1980 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Historic Preservation, 1977-1978 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Historic Preservation Program/NTHP, 1977 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Historic Pres Conference, 1976 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Historic Preservation Correspondence, 1975-1977 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Historic Preservation Proposals, 1975-1977 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Historic Preservation, 1973-1976 (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Historic District Preservation, undated (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Historic Preservation Program, undated (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Photography Tool, undated (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - National Trust Proposal, 1977-1978 (Box 3, Folder 26)
- General records, 1975-1999; RG0082 Series 4; 2 Linear feet
  Access to student records is governed by the federal Family Educational Rights and Privacy Act (FERPA), which protects the privacy of student education records. Student records are closed for 100 years from date of record creation.
  Student papers, by-laws, course information, syllabi, correspondence (Clarence Mondale, Robert Walker, departmental, etc.), Cafritz foundation, meeting minutes, Frederick Gutheim obits, newsletters, comprehensive exams, etc., 1975-1999.
  former Acc. 825
  - Assorted final papers by American studies undergraduate majors, 1999 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Proposed courses, course changes, and alterations to program, 1980 ca. (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - National Endowment for the Humanities, 1980 ca. (Box 1, Folder 3)
    General note
    Project, curriculum review
  - Historic Preservation program, 1980 ca. (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Handouts and information
  - American Studies faculty and students, 1980-1990 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    News clippings
  - Review of MA Program, 1988 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Correspondence and moemoranda
  - Dr. Bernard Mergen, 1970 ca. (Box 1, Folder 7)
    Various syllabi
  - Vernacular Architecture Program, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    Featuring American Studies faculty
  - Undergraduate requirements, 1980 ca. (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Registration sheets, 1970 ca. (Box 1, Folder 10)
    Includes course information and number of students enrolled per course
  - PhD graduate information, 1980 ca. (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Departmental newsletters, undated (Box 1, Folder 12)
    Miscellaneous
  - Departmental memoranda, 1982-1983 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    Miscellaneous subjects
  - Masters degree information, 1985 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    Proposed changes and modifications to program
  - Folklore, 1979-1980 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    Course information, joint programs, and correspondence
  - Library of Congress affiliated doctoral program, undated (Box 1, Folder 16)
    Memoranda, letters, and handwritten notes pertaining to formation, existence, and abolition of joint program in American Civilization sponsored by Library of Congress and the department
  - Major program review, 1989 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    Documentation of existing courses, support for renewal of major, memoranda, and correspondence
  - Comprehensive tool exam requirements, 1955 ca. (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Dr. Bernard Mergen correspondence, 1981-1983 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Robert H. Walker Lonely Hearts Club Band: Graduate Student organization, 1970 ca. (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - 90 hour degree program, undated (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Meeting minutes, undated (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Graduation banquet and guest books, 1988-1990 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Miscellaneous papers, departmental reviews, and course offerings, undated (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Dr. Howard Gillette correspondence, 1975-1980 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Frederick Gutheim, Historic Preservation founder, 1975-1980 (Box 1, Folder 26)
    Obituaries, clippings, essays in tribute
  - International American Studies center, 1970 ca. (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - National Endowment for the Humanities joint program renewal, undated (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - American studies program brochures, undated (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - 700 series courses and special course offerings, undated (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Faculty travel to and presentations at conferences in the field, 1980 ca. (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Special summer programs, undated (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Vernacular architecture, undated (Box 2, Folder 5)
    Alumni, information, and miscellaneous
  - United States Information Agency, 1970 ca. (Box 2, Folder 6)
    Papers and correspondence
  - Urban Planning program, undated (Box 2, Folder 7)
    Syllabi, brochure, correspondence, and requirements
  - Undergraduate majors, 1980 ca. (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Undergraduate comprehensive exams, 1960 ca. --1980 -- --ca. (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Dr. Clarence Mondale correspondence, undated (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Dr. Robert H. Walker correspondence, undated (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Part-time faculty, 1991 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Friends of Raoul Wallenberg, undated (Box 2, Folder 13)
    Organization information
  - American studies building: Photographs, undated (Box 2, Folder 14)
    Includes photo of Dr. Howard Gilette giveing walking tour in 1984
  - GWU Alumni College, 1980 ca. (Box 2, Folder 15)
    American Studies courses and information
  - AMCV, Anthropology, and History 197 Syllabi, 1970-1984 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Joint GW-Library of Congres program information, 1970-1980 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Alumni contributions, 1987-1988 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - American Studies requirements, 1980 ca. (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - American Film Institute correspondence, 1970-1980 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Five year plan, 1987 (Box 2, Folder 21)
    Correspondence, forms, and memoranda
  - Graduate Student club: Correspondence with other American Studies clubs, undated (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Cafritz Foundation, undated (Box 2, Folder 23)
    Documentation, memoranda, and correspondence
  - Columbian College--American Studies Department correspondence, 1968-1984 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Departmental reviews, 1978-1988 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Comprehensive exams, 1970 ca. (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - American Studies program bylaws, 1970 ca. (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - MA Committee information, 1988 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Library of Congress program: James H. Billington, undated (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - MA comprehensive exams, 1980-1998 (Box 2, Folder 30)
- General records, 1970-1986; RG0082 Series 5; 3.5 Linear feet
  This series contains correspondence, business records, memos, etc. Relating to the American Studies International magazine (edited by Bernard Mergen). This material dates from 1970-86.
- General records, 1959-1988; RG0082 Series 6; 0.5 Linear feet (Box 1)
  This series contains correspondence and newsletters regarding the 50th anniversary of the American Studies Pogram, notes from Robert Bolwell's class (1959). These records cover the dates 1987-88.
  - Correspondence--incoming to Howard Gillette, 1987-1988 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence--outgoing from Howard Gillette, 1987-1988 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence--miscellaneous, undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - American Studies 50th Anniversary Convocation--participant RSVP sheets, room rental sheet, etc., 1988 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - American Studies 50th Anniversary Convocation--preliminary/organizing materials, 1988 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - American Studies 50th Anniversary Convocation--speeches of panelists/lecturers, 1988 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - American Studies 50th Anniversary Convocation--press clippings, programs, 1988 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Guest book, signed by participants of 50th Anniversary Convocation, undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Notes from Robert Bolwell's class, Fall, 1959 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Social sciences 8 - fall term, 1962-1963 (Box 2, Folder 1-2)
    Scope and Contents
    Taught by J.S. Bruner and G. A. Miller.
  - Social sciences 8 - spring term, 1962-1963 (Box 2, Folder 3-5)
  - Social sciences 8, 1963-1964 (Box 2, Folder 6-8)
    Taught by J.S. Bruner.
  - Social sciences 8 lectures, 1964-1966 (Box 2, Folder 9-14)
    Taught by G. A. Miller.
- General records, 1971-1991; RG0082 Series 7; 2.0 Linear feet
  Materials in this series include the Historic American Buildings Survey report, student papers, etc., and range in date from 1971-91.
- Memorabilia, 1970; RG0082 Series 8; 5.5 Linear feet
  This series contains memorabilia and artifacts relating the the American Studies department.
  - Gas mask, 1970 ca. (Box 1)
    This gas mask belonged to Professors of American Studies and was used during the anti-Vietnam War protests. The legend goes that in the summer of 1970, Professor Howard Gillette rushed down from the roof of the American Studies building on G Street in order to stop Police from arresting one of his students during an anti-war rally. Professor Gillette wore this gasmask to protect himself from the tear gas employed by DC Police to handle crowds. In the process Gillette himself was almost arrested. Gas mask was donated to the University Archives by Professor of American Studies Barney Mergan in 2006.
- General records, 1997-2014; RG0082 Series 9
  Custodial History
  Materials transferred from the American Studies department in the Fall 2019 semester.
  - Syllabus, Fall 1997-Spring 2004 (Box 1)
  - Syllabus, Fall 2004-Fall 2009 (Box 2)
  - Syllabus, Spring 2010-Fall 2014 (Box 3)